<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: crystal | Sergey Potapov]]></title>
  <link href="http://greyblake.com/blog/categories/crystal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://greyblake.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-02-21T08:13:59+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://greyblake.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Potapov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing Crystalium organization]]></title>
    <link href="http://greyblake.com/blog/2017/08/20/announcing-crystalium-organization/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-20T13:04:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://greyblake.com/blog/2017/08/20/announcing-crystalium-organization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, dear Crystal community!</p>

<p>I discovered Crystal in December 2015. It was so exciting, I wanted to learn!
And the best way to learn a programming language is to use it. So I started looking for what
is missed in the Crystal ecosystem and what would be interesting for me to implement.
That's how I ended up with 6-8 crystal projects in my github account, that seem to be used
by other people.</p>

<p>Since that my life and my interests have changed. My focus moved to different things I'd like learn,
and I see I don't have enough time to maintain properly the projects I started.
Some of them have opened issues and pull requests for pretty long time. I thought I will address them
in few days.. or in few weeks.. But months passed and this has not happened. So I have to apologize.</p>

<p>I recall "The Cathedral and the Bazaar" book by Eric S. Raymond, who said that if one can not maintain
an open source project it should be transferred to anther maintainer if possible.</p>

<p>So I've decided to create <a href="https://github.com/crystalium">Crystalium</a> github organization,
where I moved some of my projects:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/crystal-community/icr">icr</a> - Interactive console for Crystal programming language</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/crystal-community/cossack">cossack</a> - HTTP client with middleware support</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/crystal-community/jwt">jwt</a> - JSON web tokens implemented in Crystal</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/crystal-community/kiwi">kiwi</a> - unified interface for key-value stores</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/crystal-community/leveldb">leveldb</a> - Crystal bindings for LevelDB</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/crystal-community/bloom_filter">bloom_filter</a> - bloom filter implementation</li>
</ul>


<p>If you'd like to become a member of the organization and maintain
some of these projects in collaboration with others
please let me know by sending an email to blake131313 at gmail.</p>

<p>If you are a designer and you'd like to create a logo you are welcome as well.</p>

<p>Thanks!</p>

<p>UPDATE:</p>

<p>I got an invitation to move the projects to <a href="https://github.com/crystal-community">crystal-community</a>
what makes sense to me. I believe it's a better option, than creating another separate organization.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
